A Guide to the Hannah Flagg Gould Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7633
Hannah Flagg Gould Collection 1822-1893
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7633
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit 1964 Jul 21
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Poem, " Miss Hannah Gould's epitaphs ", 1822 Mar; AMs, 4 p.
    [36 humorous epitaphs on "local celebrities" including herself.]
  - Poem, " The Sad Return ", 1838 Jan; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Laments young woman who died while traveling abroad.]
  - Poem, " Sunrise at Sea " (excerpt), 1840 Sep; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Describes the sun rising over the ocean.]
  - Poem, " Scripture Hymn ", 1848 Apr 19; AMsS, 3 p.
    [Urges Christians to live for the Lord and spread his word.]
  - Poem, " A Name in the Sand ", 1849 Apr 23; AMsS, 1 p. w/newspaper copy
    [Comments on the transitoriness of life; asserts that the eternal record of each human existence is kept by God.]
  - Poem, " Earth and Heaven ", 1854 Aug 16; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Compares the transitory pleasure of life on earth with the eternal delights of heaven.]
  - First verse of poem, " We Are Spirits ", 1858 Nov 30; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Proclaims the fleeting uncertainty of earthly existence.]
  - Poem, " The Sprouting Horn ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Describes a water spout and compares it human existence.]
  - Poem, " Serenade ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Voyager's farewell to a loved on being left behind.]
  - Poem, " The Sailor Boy ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Laments the death at sea of a young sailor.]
- Letters
  - Hannah Flagg Gould to Rev. John A. Clark, 1837 Feb 10; ALS, 1 p.
    [Responds to request for some of her verses; asks his help in contacting [President Colton] of Bristol College regarding an article he published in
    The Religious Souvenir
    includes note on reverse of backing sheet in another hand, "Dr. James Gregory, Professor of Medicine in Edinburgh, Author of "Philosophical Essays"-the "Conspectus."]
  - Hannah Flagg Gould to Dear Sir, 1839 Jun 7; ALS, 2 p.
    [Responds to request for a piece to be published in
    Ship and Shipments
    expresses pleasure at being introduced to Mr. Cutter and Mr. Mellen whose writing she admires.]
  - Hannah Flagg Gould to Elias Nason, 1847 Oct 2; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for loaned books; invites him and his brother to call to discuss adapting some of her pieces to melodies.]
  - Hannah Flagg Gould to D. N. Haskell, 1857 May 25; ALS, 3 p.
    [Decries his use of her poem "
    A Name in the Sand
    " in his publication the
    Transcript
    in mutilated form and without acknowledging the author.]
  - Hannah Flagg Gould to Messrs. James Monroe & Co., 1860 Jan 14; ALS, 1 p.
    [Requests 40 copies of an unnamed item, for which she will pay $5.]
  - Hannah Flagg Gould to Mr. Keeler, n. d.; ALS, 3 p.
    [Regrets having no letters or papers on revolutionary days to add to his collection; reminisces about her father's war experiences from Lexington to West Point. ]
  - Hannah Flagg Gould to Helen C. Knight, n. d.; ALS (fragment), 2 p.
    [Responds to request for a literary contribution.]
  - Hannah Flagg Gould to Anne T., n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Invites her to join Gould and other guests for a social evening.]
- Miscellaneous
  - Transcript, 1893 Dec 6; Clipping
    [Letters to the Editor admonishing the use of an incorrect title for Hannah Flagg Gould's poem "
    It Snows
    " and its publication without credit to the author.]
  - " An American Poetess ", n. d.; Clipping
    [Newspaper article by H. E. H. reminiscing about Hannah Flagg Gould, whom she had met as a child, and discussing her poetic style.]
  - Poem, " A Name in the Sand ", Clipping
    [See manuscripts.]